{"tossups": [{"question": "This man commissioned the Hands of Victory arch formed by two crossing swords. During this man\u2019s reign, he hired a nurse and calligrapher to write a copy of the Qu\u2019ran with 27 liters of his own blood to be stored in a mosque named after the Mother of All Battles, a phrase this dictator used to describe a conflict triggered by his invasion of Kuwait. For the point, name this dictator deposed in the 2003 Iraq War.", "answer": "Saddam<b> Hussein</b> Abd al-Majid al-Tikriti", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "For the point, name this Germanic group, led by Alaric and Theodoric in the fifth century CE, the western group of the two main divisions of Goths.", "answer": "<b> Visigoth</b>s (prompt on \u201cGoths\u201d before mentioned; prompt on barbarians; prompt on Germans before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Isaac Kidd was killed on the bridge of this ship. Fires on the nearby repair ship<em> Vestal</em> were blown out by a shockwave caused when an ammunition magazine detonated on this ship. \u201cBlack tears\u201d continue to seep from this ship, which was not salvaged after an explosion that killed 1,177 men. For the point, name this battleship sunk during the Pearl Harbor attacks, commemorated by a floating war memorial.", "answer": "USS<b> Arizona</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One play about this war concerns a power struggle between a sausage-seller and Cleon, who supported this war. Another play about this war, written after the disastrous Sicilian Expedition, describes a group of women taking an oath around a bowl full of wine. Those women refuse to have sex with their husbands unless they agree to end this war. Aristophanes\u2019 411 BC play<em> Lysistrata</em> protested, for the point, what war between Athens and Sparta?", "answer": "<b> Peloponnesian</b> War", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "In this battle, Francis Randall\u2019s heart attack caused the only fatality for the winning side. It began when Charles Gridley was told \u201cyou may fire when ready,\u201d and it ended with the near total destruction of the Spanish fleet, crippling them in the Pacific theater of the Spanish-American War. For the point, name this naval battle fought near the capital of the Philippines.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Manila Bay</b> Page 1", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Charles de Bourbon was said to have been shot by Benvenuto Cellini while attempting to perform this action, which was resisted from the Castel Sant\u2019Angelo. One leader is said to have proclaimed \u201cvae victis\u201dwhile measuring tribute after performing this action, which occurred after the Battle of the Allia. One of these actions led to the deposition of Romulus Augustulus. For the point, name this action, performed by troops under Brennus, Alaric, and Odoacer, which involved partially destroying a city in central Italy.", "answer": "<b> sack</b>ing<b> Rome</b> (prompt on \u201ccapturing Rome\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This President ordered the dishonorable discharge of 167 innocent black soldiers in the Brownsville Affair. Conservation of the environment, control of corporations, and consumer protection were the \u201cthree C\u2019s\u201d of this President\u2019s Square Deal. For the point, name this president who succeeded William McKinley and unsuccessfully ran for a third term as a Bull Moose candidate.", "answer": "<b> T</b>heodore (or<b> T</b>eddy)<b> Roosevelt</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In a siege of this city, Simon bar Giora and John of Giscala were captured. That siege of this city is commemorated by Rome\u2019s Temple of Peace and the Arch of Titus, and is mourned on Tisha B\u2019Av. Another siege of this city by Pompey the Great resulted in Roman conquering of Judea. For the point, name this city where the First and Second Temples on Temple Mount were destroyed.", "answer": "<b> Jerusalem</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This man decreed that his family would be heirs to the unified Low Countries in a 1549 pragmatic sanction. Adrian of Utrecht served as regent for this ruler during the Revolt of the Comuneros. This ruler agreed to the Peace of Augsburg with the Schmalkaldic League, whom this ruler defeated at the Battle of Muhlberg. This ruler sponsored Ferdinand Magellan\u2019s expeditions and fathered Philip II of Spain. For the point, name this Holy Roman Emperor who was also the King of Spain.", "answer": "<b> Charles V</b>, Holy Roman Emperor (or<b> Charles I of Spain</b> or<b> Carlos I of Spain</b>, prompt on\u201cCharles\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The opening of this piece quotes the hymn \u201cTroparion of the Holy Cross.\u201d This piece, popularized in America by Arthur Fiedler and the Boston Pops, commemorates the Battle of Borodino and culminates with a rendition of \u201cGod Save the Tsar.\u201d It represents Napoleon\u2019s invading army with \u201cLa Marsellaise\u201d[lah MAR-sigh-ehz] and includes sixteen artillery blasts in the score. For the point, what overture by Peter Tchaikovsky is often played on July 4th and includes cannon fire?", "answer": "The<b> 1812 Overture</b> or The<b> Year 1812</b> Page 2", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In this country, the Lion of Al-lat was destroyed in May 2015. One leader of this country is opposed by the FSA and the Islamic Front. Palmyra is controlled by ISIS in this country, where Bashar al-Assad has been opposed by rebels since 2011. For the point, name this middle eastern country embattled by civil war in cities like Aleppo and its capital, Damascus.", "answer": "<b> Syria</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "On the right side of one of this artist\u2019s paintings, a man in a turban rides a black horse rearing over a group of anguished victims of the Greek War of Independence. In another work celebrating the July Revolution, this artist painted a boy wielding two pistols to the right of a bare-breasted woman waving the tri-color. For the point, name this painter of<em> The Massacre at Chios</em> and<em> Liberty Leading the People</em>.", "answer": "(Ferdinand Victor) Eugene<b> Delacroix</b> [oo-ZHEN dell-ah-QUA]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This politician responded to Samuel Seabury\u2019s criticism of the First Continental Congress by writing <em>A Full Vindication of the Measures of Congress</em>. His Assumption Act was passed after compromising to locate a nation\u2019s capital on the Potomac River and was influenced by his<em> First Report on Public Credit</em>. He debated with Thomas Jefferson over the Necessary and Proper Clause that later allowed the formation of the First Bank of the United States. For the point, name this first U.S. Secretary of the Treasury.", "answer": "Alexander<b> Hamilton</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This battle featured the 1077th Anti-Aircraft Regiment, which was composed entirely of women, and a stubborn defense of Pavlov\u2019s House. Georgy Zhukov implemented a plan known as Operation Uranus to encircle Friedrich Paulus\u2019s German 6th Army during this battle. The Nazi forces in this battle sought to gain access to the oil fields near the Volga River. For the point, name this World War II battle that served as a turning point for the USSR.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Stalingrad</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The Brent Blend is one classification of this commodity, which is labeled \u201csweet\u201d if it has low sulfur concentration. Benon Sevan led the Australian Wheat Board\u2019s program that allowed the sale of this commodity to Saddam Hussein\u2019s government, which received kickbacks and avoided sanctions by selling it to that program. For the point, name this commodity, a fossil fuel whose crude form is drilled and refined to create gasoline.", "answer": "crude<b> oil</b> (accept descriptors; do not accept natural gas)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Legend says that this battle\u2019s first cannonball landed on a British officers\u2019 dining table. This battle included a brief diversionary attack on the Fusiliers launched by Rochambeau [roh-SHAM-boh] before the Americans assaulted Redoubt 10. Another legend says that the tune \u201cThe World Turned Upside Down\u201dwas played by the losing side as Lord Cornwallis surrendered to George Washington. For the point, name this battle that effectively ended the American Revolution.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Yorktown</b> Page 3", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This book notes that only man has acquired the \u201csignificant power to alter the nature of the world\u201din describing the \u201cObligation to Endure.\u201d \u201cA strange blight crept over\u201d a hypothetical town in this work\u2019s opening, \u201cA Fable for Tomorrow.\u201d The EPA was formed after public reaction to this book\u2019s description of the effects of DDT and other pesticides. For the point, name this 1962 environmentalist text by Rachel Carson.", "answer": "<b> Silent Spring</b> Page 4", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "The Green Bank device of this type is at the center of the U.S. National Radio Quiet Zone. The Gregorian and Cassegrain reflector types were improvements on the first known one of these devices, designed by Hans Lippershey. A simple reflecting type of these instruments using two mirrors was developed by and named for Isaac Newton. Galileo used one of these of his own design to discover the four largest moons of Jupiter. for the point, name these devices used for remote viewing of celestial objects.", "answer": "<b> telescope</b> (accept<b> radio telescope</b> until \u201cimprovements\u201d)", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Attempts to centralize the meat industry in this city were protested by butchers using the 14th Amendment, resulting in the Slaughterhouse Cases. Michael Brown was told \u201cyou\u2019re doing one heck of a job\u201d while being incompetent in this city. Edward Pakenham was killed in a battle fought in this city after the signing of the Treaty of Ghent; that battle was a victory for Andrew Jackson. For the point, name this city, which was devastated by Hurricane Katrina and is the largest in Louisiana.", "answer": "<b> New Orleans</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In this battle, Cynaegirus [ky-nee-gir-us] unsuccessfully tried to pull an enemy trireme back to shore, only for his hand to be cut off. Eretria had previously been captured by the losing side in this battle, which was led by Datis and Artaphernes [ar-ta-FAIR-nees]. The tyrant Hippias was present at this battle, after which Pheidippides [fay-uh-DIP-ih-dees] carried the information of this Greek victory to Athens. For the point, name ancient battle that saw Miltiades [mill-TIE-uh-dees] lead Athenian forces to victory against an invasion force sent by Darius the Great.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Marathon</b> Page 5", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Napoleon III urged this man to claim the throne of a foreign nation that was held by Benito Juarez. For the point, name this Austrian who was King of Mexico.", "answer": "great<b> flood</b>s (or<b> deluge</b>, accept any additional information) <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if moderator botches a question. (1) This man married Charlotte of Belgium, who later changed her name to Carlota. This monarch\u2019s alliance with a country\u2019s leader was influenced by his dismissal as Viceroy of Lombardy- Venetia by his brother Franz-Josef I. A Manet painting that depicted the execution of this leader was influenced by Francisco Goya\u2019s Third of May, 1808. Napoleon III urged this man to claim the throne of a foreign nation that was held by Benito Juarez. For the point, name this Austrian who was King of Mexico. ANSWER:<b> Maximilian</b> I of Mexico Page 6", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}